<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The foundation of Christian religion gathered into sixe principles. And it is to be learned of ignorant people, that they may be fit to heare sermons with profit, and to receiue the Lords Supper with comfort.</title>
            <author>Perkins, William, 1588-1602.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845985</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845985</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10919</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10919)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1668:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The foundation of Christian religion gathered into sixe principles. And it is to be learned of ignorant people, that they may be fit to heare sermons with profit, and to receiue the Lords Supper with comfort.</title>
                  <author>Perkins, William, 1588-1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Legatt, printer to the Vniuersitie of Cambridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's device on title page and on verso of C8, final page.</note>
                  <note>Cropped and tightly bound affecting some text.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10919:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10919:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10919:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10919:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FOVNDATION OF CHRISTIAN RELIGION GATHERED INTO SIXE Principles.</p>
            <p>And it is to be learned of ignorant people, that they may be fit to heare Sermons with profit, and to receiue the Lords Supper with comfort.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 119. verſ. 20.</bibl>
               <p>The <hi>entrance</hi> into thy words ſheweth light, and giueth vnderſtanding to the <hi>ſimple.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>ALMA MATER CANTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BRIGIA</head>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <q xml:lang="lat">HINC LVCEM ET POCVLA SACRA</q>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>Iohn Legate,</hi> Printer to the Vniuerſitie of Cambridge. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10919:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10919:3"/>
            <head>To all ignorant people that deſire to be inſtructed.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Oore people, your manner is to ſoth vp your ſelues, as though you were in a moſt happy eſtate but if the matter come to a iuſt triall, it will fall out farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, For yee leade your liues in great ignorance, as may appeare by theſe common opinions which follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 That faith is a mans good meaning and his ſeruing of God.</item>
               <item>2 That God is ſerued by the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the tenne commaundements, the Lords prayer, and the Creede.</item>
               <item>3 That ye haue beleeued in Chriſt euer ſince you could remember.</item>
               <item>4 That it is pitrie that hee ſhould liue which doth any whit doubt of his ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</item>
               <item>5 That none can tell whether he ſhall be ſaued or no certainely, but that all men muſt be of a good beliefe.</item>
               <item>6 That howſoeuer a man liue, yet if hee call vpon God on his death bedde, and ſay, <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon mee,</hi> and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10919:4"/>goe away like a lambe, hee is certainely ued.</item>
               <item>7 That if any bee ſtrangely viſited, he is either taken with a planet, or bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</item>
               <item>8 That a man may lawfully ſweare when hee ſpeaketh nothing but the troth and ſweares by nothing but that which is good, as by faith and troth.</item>
               <item>9 That a preacher is a good man no longer then hee is in the Pulpit. <hi>They thinke all like themſelues.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>10 That a man may repent when hee will, becauſe the Scripture ſaith, <hi>At what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſinne, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12 That it is an eaſier thing to pleaſe God, then to pleaſe our neighbour.</item>
               <item>13 That yee can keepe the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements as well as God will giue you leaue.</item>
               <item>13 That it is ſafeſt to doe in religion as moſt doe.</item>
               <item>14 That merry ballads and bookes, as <hi>Sk<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ggin, Beuis of Southampton, &amp;c.</hi> are good to driue away the time, and to remooue heart qualmes.</item>
               <item>15 That yee ſerue God with all your hearts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that you would be ſorry elſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10919:4"/>
16 That a man need not heare ſo many Sermons, except hee could follow them better.</item>
               <item>17 That a man which commeth at no Sermons, may as well beleeue, as hee which heares all the Sermons in the world.</item>
               <item>18 That ye know all the Preacher can tell you. For hee can ſay nothing, but that euery man is a ſinner that wee muſt loue our neighbours as our ſelues, that euery man muſt be ſaued by Chriſt: and all this ye can tell as well as he.</item>
               <item>19 That it was a good world, when the old religion was, becauſe all things were cheape.</item>
               <item>20 That drinking and bezeling in the alehouſe or tauerne is good fellowſhip, and ſhewes a good kind nature, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines neighbourhood.</item>
               <item>21 That a man may ſweare by the Maſſe, becauſe it is nothing now: and by<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Lady, becauſe ſhee it gone out of the countrey.</item>
               <item>22 That euery man muſt bee for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and God for vs all.</item>
               <item>23 That a man may make of his owne whatſoeuer he can.</item>
               <item>24 That if a man remember to ſay
<pb facs="tcp:10919:5"/>his praiers in the morning (though he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnderſtand them) hee hath bleſſed himſelfe for all the day following.</item>
               <item>25 That a man praieth when hee ſaith the ten commandements.</item>
               <item>26 That a man eates his maker in the Sacrament.</item>
               <item>27 That if a man be no adulterer, no theefe, no murtherer, &amp; do no man harme, he is a right honeſt man.</item>
               <item>28 That a man neede not to haue any knowledge of religion, becauſe he is not book-learned.</item>
               <item>29 That one may haue a good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning when hee ſaith and doth that which is euill.</item>
               <item>30 That a man may goe to wizzards, called wiſe men, for counſell: becauſe God hath prouided a ſalue for euery ſore.</item>
               <item>31 That yee are to bee excuſed in all your doings, becauſe the beſt men are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</item>
               <item>32 That yee haue ſo ſtrong a faith in Chriſt, that no euill company can hurt you.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe and ſuch like ſayings, what argue they but your groſſe ignorance? Now where
<pb facs="tcp:10919:5"/>ignorance raineth, there raignes ſin: and where ſinne raignes, there the diuell rules: and where he rules, men are in a damnable caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye will reply vnto me thus that yee are not ſo bad as I would make you. If neede be you can ſay the Creed, the Lords praier, &amp; the ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: and therfore ye will be of Gods beliefe, ſay all men what they will, and you defie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell from your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſwer againe, that it is not ſufficient to ſay all theſe without booke, vnles ye can vnderſtand the meaning of the words, and be able to make a right vſe of the commandements, of the Creed, of the Lords prayer, by applying them inwardly to your hearts and conſciences, and outwardly to your liues and conuerſation. This is the very point in which ye faile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And for a helpe in this your ignorance, to bring you to true knowledge, vnfained faith and ſound repentance, heere I haue ſet downe the principall points of Chriſtian Religion in ſixe plaine and eaſie rules: euen ſuch as the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plest may eaſily learne: and hereunto is adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an expoſition of them word by word. If yee doe want other good directions, then vſe this my labour for your good inſtruction. In reading of it, firſt learne the ſixe principles: and when you haue them without booke, and the meaning of the withall, then learne the expoſition
<pb facs="tcp:10919:6"/>alſo: which beeing well conceiued, and in ſome me aſure felt in the heart, ye ſhall be able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by Sermons, whereas now ye cannot: and the ordinary parts of the Catechiſme, namely, the ten Commandements, the Creeds, the Lords prayer, and the inſtitution of the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſhall more eaſily be vnderſtood.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>William Perkins.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="religious_tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:10919:6"/>
            <head>The Foundation of <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> gathered into ſixe Principles.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head type="sub">The firſt Principle,</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſtion.</label>
                  <hi>VVHat doeſt thou beleeue concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> 
                  <hi>There is one God, Creator and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor of all things, diſtinguiſhed into the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Proofes out of the word of God.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. There is a God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the inuiſible things of him, that is, his eternall power and Godhead,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20</note> are ſeene by the creation of the world, beeing conſidered in his workes, to the intent that they ſhould be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe.</p>
                  <p>Neuertheleſſe, hee left not himſelfe without witneſſe, in thou be did good,<note place="margin">Act. 14.17</note> and gaue vs rame from heauen, and fruitfull ſeaſons, fulfilling our hearts with foode and gladneſſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2. There is one God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.4</note>Concerning therefore meates ſacrificed to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:10919:7"/>idols, wee know that an idoll is nothing in the world: and that there is none other God but one.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3. He is Creator of all things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the beginning God created the heauens and the earth.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en. 1.1.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Through faith we vnderſtand, that the world was ordained by the word of God:<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eb. 11.5.</note> ſo that the things which we ſee, are not made of things which did appeare.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4. He is gouernour of all things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The eies of the Lord in euery place behold the euill and the good.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rou. 15.3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea, and all the haires of our heads are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.30.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5. Diſtinguiſhed into the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And Ieſus when hee was baptized, came ſtraight out of the water:<note place="margin">Mat. 3.16.</note> and loe, the heauens were opened vnto him, and Iohn ſaw the Spirit of God deſcending like a Doue, and lighting vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</p>
                  <p>And loe a voice came from heauen, ſaying, This is my wel beloued Sonne,<note place="margin">Verſe 17.</note> in whom I am well pleaſed.</p>
                  <p>For there are three which beare record in heauen,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.7.</note> the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:10919:7"/>
               <head>The ſecond Principle.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> 
                  <hi>What doeſt thou beleeue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning man and concerning thine owne ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> All men are wholly corrupted with ſinne through <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and ſo are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſlaues of <hi>Satan,</hi> and guilty of eternall damnation.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. All men are corrupted with ſinne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As it is written, There is none righteous,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.10</note> no not one.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2. They are wholly corrupted.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now the very God of peace ſanctifie you throughout,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Theſ 5.13.</note> 
                     <hi>and I pray God that your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and bodie, may bee kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This I ſay therefore and teſtifie in the Lord, that yee hencefoorth walke not as other Gentiles walke in vanity of their minde.<note place="margin">Eph. 4.17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hauing their cogitation darkened,<note place="margin">Verſ. 18.</note> and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrangers from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the hardues of their hearts.</p>
                  <p>When the Lord ſaw that the wickedneſſe of man was great in the earth,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.5.</note> and all the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the thought of his heart were onely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill continually.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:10919:8"/>
                     <hi>3. Through Adams fall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore as by one man, ſinne entred int<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo dea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> went ouer all men,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om. 5.21.</note> for ſo much as all men hau<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſinned.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4. And ſo are become ſlaues of Satan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherein in times paſt ye walked according to the courſe of the world,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.2.</note> and after the Princ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that ruleth in the aire, euen the ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience.</p>
                  <p>For as much then as the children were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of fleſh and blood,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note> hee alſo himſelfe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tooke part with them that he might deſtroy through death, him that had the power of death, that is, the diuell.</p>
                  <p>In whom the God of this world hath blinded the minds,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> that is, of Infidels, that the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, which is the image of God, ſhould not ſhine vnto them.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5. And guilty of eternall damnation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For as many as are of the workes of the law,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note> are vnder the curſe: for it is written, Curſed is euery man that continueth not in all things, which are written in the booke of the law, to doe them. Likewiſe then as by
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:10919:8"/>the offence of one, the fault came on all men to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ondemnation: ſo by the iuſtifying of one, the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enefit abounded toward all men to the inſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation of life.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.1</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>The third Principle.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> 
                  <hi>What meanes is there for thee to eſcape this damnable eſtate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> 
                  <hi>Ieſus Chriſt the eternall Sonne of God, being made man, by his death vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, and by his righteouſnes, hath perfectly alone by himſelfe, accompliſhed all things that are needfull for the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. Ieſus Chriſt the eternall Sonne of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the word was made fleſh, and dwelt among vs, and wee ſaw the glory thereof,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.14.</note> as the glory of the onely begotten (Sonne) of the Father, full of grace and truth.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2. Being made man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For hee in no ſort tooke the Angels, but hee tooke the ſeede of Abraham.<note place="margin">Heb. 2.16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3. By his death vpon the croſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions,<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.5.</note> hee was broken for our iniquities: the chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our peace was vpon him, and with his ſtripes weare healed.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4. And by his righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 5.15</note>For as by one mans deſobedience many
<pb facs="tcp:10919:9"/>were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one ſha<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> many alſo be made righteous.</p>
                  <p>For he hath made him to be ſin for vs, which knew no ſinne,<note place="margin">Cor. 5.21</note> that we ſhould bee made the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God in him.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5. Hath perfectly</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherfore he is alſo able perfectly to ſaue them that come vnto God by him,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eb. 7.27.</note> ſeeing hee euer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to make interceſſion for them.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6. Alone by himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither is there ſaluation in any other for among men there is giuen none other name vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der auen,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ct. 4 12.</note> whereby we muſt be ſaued.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7. Accompliſhed all things needfull for the ſaluation of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And he is the reconciliation for our ſinnes: and not for ours onely,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.2.</note> but alſo for the ſins of the whole world.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>The fourth Principle.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Q.</label> 
                  <hi>But how maieſt thou be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of Chriſt and his benefits?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>A.</label> 
                  <hi>A man of a contrite and humble ſpirit, by faith alone apprehending and applying Chriſt with all his merits vnto himſelfe, is iuſtified before God, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10919:9"/>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1. A man of contrite and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpirit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thus ſaith hee that is high and excellent, Hee that inhabiteth the eternitie,<note place="margin">Eſa. 57.1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> whoſe name is the holy one; I dwell in the high and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to reuiue the Spirit of the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to giue life to them that are of a contrite heart.</p>
                  <p>The ſacrifices of God, are a contrite ſpirit,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.1.</note> a contrite and a broken heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2. By faith alone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As ſoone as Ieſus heard that word ſpoken, he ſaid vnto the ruler of the Synagogue,<note place="margin">Mark. 5.3.</note> Bee not afraid, onely beleeue.</p>
                  <p>So Moſes made a ſerpent of braſſe, and ſet it vp for a ſigne,<note place="margin">Numb. 21 19.</note> and when a Serpent had bitten a man, then hee looked to the Serpent of braſſe, and liued.</p>
                  <p>And as Moſes lift vp the Serpent in the wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.14.</note> ſo muſt the Sonne of man bee lifted vp.</p>
                  <p>That whoſoeuer beleeueth in him,<note place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> ſhould not periſh, but haue eternall life.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3. Apprehending and applying Chriſt with all his merits vnto himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But as many as recciued him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> to them hee gaue</p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
